{"tossups": [{"question": "This case was originally filed against H.G. Cochrane who retired soon after. The winner of this case was forced to sit for a second trial during which he was represented by Fred Turner. This case overturned the \u201cspecial circumstances\u201d requirement written in<em> Betts v. Brady</em>. In this case, Abe Fortas argued on the behalf of a defendant who had broken into a Florida pool hall. The public defender system was expanded as a result of, for ten points, what case that expanded the accused\u2019s right to an attorney to states.", "answer": "<b> Gideon</b> v.<b> Wainwright</b> (accept either underlined name)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This battle\u2019s loser boasted that \u201can arm when cut off cannot grow again, but a shorn beard will.\u201dMarco Bragadin was flayed alive after buying time for this battle\u2019s winning side to assemble a fleet. This battle was prompted by the siege of Famagusta and the loss of one participant\u2019s colony of Cyprus. Miguel Cervantes lost an arm fighting under Don Juan of Austria in this battle, the last great engagement between galleys. For ten points, identify this naval victory for the Holy League over the Ottomans in 1571.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Lepanto</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Peter Malkin\u2019s memoirs about this event inspired a 2018 film starring Ben Kingsley as this event\u2019s subject and also featuring Michael Aronov as Zvi Aharoni. During this event, a team led by Rafi Eitan raided a home on Garibaldi Street. This event, the subject of the film<em> Operation Finale</em>, resulted in agents of Mossad drugging a man for his flight out of Argentina in May 1960. For ten points, name this event that allowed a Nazi to be put on trial in Israel.", "answer": "Mossad/Israel\u2019s<b> capture</b> (or synonyms) of Adolf<b> Eichmann</b> (accept equivalents; prompt on partial answers; do not accept Eichmann\u2019s trial)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "James Martin Eder revolutionized this industry at the \u201cLa Manuelita\u201d hacienda with steam power. The Mascate War was fought between Portuguese merchants and landowners of this industry in Pernambuco. John Drax used slave labor to develop this industry in Barbados, which later utilized Benjamin Delessert\u2019s method of extracting this industry\u2019s commodity from beet roots. For ten points, name this industry central to the Caribbean colonies, products from which were used to make rum and molasses.", "answer": "<b> sugar</b>cane industry (prompt on \u201cmolasses\u201d industry until mention) Page 1", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Followers of this man broke into the house of Rebecca Vaughan and killed while she prayed. After being found hiding among the Nottoway by Benjamin Phipps, this man asked \u201cWas Christ not crucified?\u201d The blueish-green appearance of the Sun, possibly caused by an eruption of Mount St. Helens, was interpreted by this man as a message from God to begin one event. Thomas Gray recorded the \u201cconfessions\u201d of this man who may have ordered his followers to \u201ckill all the white people.\u201d For ten points, name this slave who led an 1831 rebellion in Southampton County, Virginia.", "answer": "Nat<b> Turner</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "During this conflict, one side\u2019s declaration that they were preparing the Samson Option prompted the United States to provide aid in Operation Nickel Grass. This conflict commenced with a surprise attack in Operation Badr on the Bar Lev Line. Henry Kissinger\u2019s shuttle diplomacy helped bring an end to this conflict, the failure to prevent which led Golda Meir to resign. For ten points, name this conflict in which Arab forces surprised Israel on the Day of Atonement.", "answer": "<b> Yom Kippur</b> War", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s first term as prime minister ended after Daniel O\u2019Connell allied with Lord Melbourne to block any law this man proposed. This man sparked the Bedchamber Crisis and penned the Tamworth Manifesto, one of the cornerstones of the Conservative Party. This man resigned after siding with the opposition to repeal the Corn Laws in the wake of the Irish Potato Famine. For ten points, identify this British prime minister who founded the London Metropolitan Police Force.", "answer": "Robert<b> Peel</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Steve Bales accepted an award for his role in this mission for saying \u201cGo\u201d when he could have said\u201cStop\u201d or \u201cWait.\u201d A planned speech in case this mission failed opens with \u201cFate has ordained\u201d that men who went to \u201cexplore in peace\u201d will now \u201crest in peace.\u201d After completing a landing procedure in this mission, its participants radioed Houston to say \u201cThe Eagle has landed.\u201d For ten points, name this mission in which Neil Armstrong said \u201cThat\u2019s one small step for man\u201d after landing on the moon.", "answer": "<b> Apollo 11</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A work by this composer was adapted from the last two tableau of his posthumously published<em> Press</em> <em>Celebrations Music</em>. The Biafran national anthem was adapted from a melody by this composer, as was the hymn<em> Be Still, My Soul</em>. This composer of seven symphonies left his final one, in C major, unfinished. One of this composer\u2019s works was censored during his country\u2019s independence movement from Russia at the start of the 20th century. For ten points, name this composer of<em> Finlandia</em>.", "answer": "Jean<b> Sibelius</b> Page 2", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "One side in this trial was represented by Samuel Phillips who was opposed by Milton Joseph Cunningham, a man arrested during Reconstruction for restoring white supremacy. Henry Billings Brown reasoned that the matters of \u201chealth, safety, and morals\u201d belong to the state government in this majority decision for this case. The lone dissent in this case argued that \u201cour constitution is color-blind.\u201d A violation of Louisiana\u2019s Separate Car Act prompted, for ten points, what case which created the doctrine of \u201cseparate but equal?\u201d", "answer": "<b> Plessy</b> v. Ferguson", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "One work builds on Joan Riviere\u2019s comment that a variant of this word is a \u201cmasquerade,\u201d claiming that this word is open to \u201cresignification\u201d because this word\u2019s definition is performative and the category this word implies is invalid. In another work, one author argues that this word is defined as a dialectic\u201cOther\u201d and quipped, \u201cone is not born, but becomes\u201d this word. For ten points, name this word at the center of Judith Butler\u2019s<em> Gender Trouble</em> and Simone de Beauvoir\u2019s<em> The Second Sex</em>.", "answer": "<b> \u201cwoman\u201d</b> BONUS:<em> Gender Trouble</em> also engages what thinker\u2019s<em> History of Sexuality</em>, which examines historical discourse to argue that sex is a social construct and subject to societal forms of power? ANSWER: Michel<b> Foucault</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "Prior warning of this event was given by a chauffeur nicknamed Jean-Pierre. The Batwa people are often called the \u201cforgotten victims\u201d of this event, which was spurred by propaganda from the RTLM radio station. Romeo Dallaire\u2019s UNAMIR failed to prevent this event, which began after the death of President Habyarimana. This event was mainly perpetuated by the Interahamwe militia and came to an end when RPF forces captured Kigali. For ten points, name this 1994 genocide of Tutsis by Hutus.", "answer": "<b> Rwandan Genocide</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This organization intervened in the Bosnian War by enforcing Operation Deny Flight. For ten points, name this mutual defense organization formed after World War II with the primary goal of countering the USSR.", "answer": "<b> NATO</b> (or<b> North Atlantic Treaty Organization</b> or<b> North Atlantic Alliance</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A communist party leader from this modern country, Edvard Kadelj, was accidentally shot by Jovan Veselinov, who was aiming at a wild boar. This country\u2019s DEMOS party helped form its first government, after which it declared independence, leading to the Brioni Agreement after winning the Ten Day War and beginning a general breakup of a Balkan conglomerate state. The historical region of Carniola is the site of, for ten points, what former Yugoslav republic\u2019s capital of Ljubljana?", "answer": "<b> Slovenia</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "To facilitate this event, a secret communication channel called \u201cPrivate Blank Check\u201d was set-up by two participants. Medhi Hasehmi may have been executed due to his role in this event, as he was arrested soon after leaking information to<em> Ash-Shiraa</em>. Fawn Hall defended herself by saying \u201cWe shred everything\u201dafter being implicated in this scandal. John Poindexter resigned as National Security Adviser due to this scandal. For ten points, name this Reagan-era scandal in which weapons were sold to a Middle Eastern country in order to fund a Nicaraguan rebel group.", "answer": "<b> Iran-Contra</b> affair (prompt on Irangate)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This political party\u2019s official ideology of \u201cintegral humanism\u201d was developed in the 1960s. This party has historically advocated for the abrogation of Article 370. This organization and the VHP were responsible for the demolition of a (+) mosque in 1992 located in Ayodhya. This party\u2019s current leader demonetized his country\u2019s high-denomination banknotes in 2016 and served as Chief Minister of (*)</b> Gujarat during 2002 anti-Muslim riots. For ten points, name this Hindu nationalist party led by Narendra Modi, a frequent rival to the Indian National Congress Party.", "answer": "<b> B</b>harata<b> J</b>anata<b> P</b>arty [accept<b> BJP</b>]", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b>In the aftermath of this event, Roswell Mason ordered Philip Sheridan to declare martial law. A warehouse constructed by Gurdon (+) Hubbard to supply Fort Dearborn with meat was destroyed in this event. This event resulted in the destruction of the luxurious Palmer House which had opened just 13 days prior. Only seven (*) </b> buildings survived in the area affected by this event, including the city\u2019s water tower. Mrs O\u2019Learly\u2019s cow is incorrectly claimed to be the cause of, for ten points, what 1871 disaster that heavily damaged a large Illinois city?", "answer": "Great<b> Chicago Fire</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>In one of this artist\u2019s unfinished works, George Sand sat next to Chopin at a piano. One of this artist\u2019s works depicts Jacob wrestling with the angel and is frescoed on a wall next</b> <b>to this artist\u2019s</b><em><b> Heliodorus Chased from the Temple</b></em><b> in the (+)</b> <b>Church of Saint-Sulpice.</b> <b>This artist was inspired by Gericault\u2019s</b><em><b> Raft of the Medusa</b></em><b> in a work where tormented souls attack a vessel carrying a red-hooded figure and (*) </b> Virgil, the<em> Barque of Dante</em>. In this artist\u2019s best known work, a boy waves a pistol next to a woman carrying the French tricolor in the July Revolution. For ten points, name this artist of<em> Liberty Leading the People</em>.", "answer": "Eug`ene<b> Delacroix</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "<b>The February Patent established this state\u2019s Imperial Council, deputies to which were elected by a curiae system. An heir apparent to this state committed suicide along with</b> <b>Baroness Mary Vetsera in the (+)</b> <b>Mayerling Incident. Ferenc Deak [dee-ack] and Gyula</b> <b>Mayerling Incident. Ferenc Deak [dee-ack] and Gyula</b> <b>Andrassy were instrumental to establishing this state in the 1867 (*)</b> <b>Andrassy were instrumental to establishing this state in the 1867 (*)</b> Ausgleich agreement. The Allied Powers dissolved this state with the separate treaties of Saint-Germain-en-Laye and Trianon. For ten points, name this dual monarchy whose 1914 declaration of war against Serbia triggered the First World War.", "answer": "<b> Austria-Hungary</b> (accept<b> Austro-Hungarian</b> Empire; accept<b> Austria</b>n Empire until\u201ccuriae\u201d; prompt on \u201cAustria\u201d afterwards; do not accept or prompt on \u201cHungary\u201d alone)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>Seven men were beaten by police officers in Los Angeles in 1951 during an incident named for this day. In 1963, over 500 Cypriots were killed during an incident named for this day. Edmund the Martyr was (+) anointed on this day, which was banned by Puritans in 1647. 40 days named for St. Martin of Tours precede this holiday, on which Charlemagne was (*)</b> crowned emperor in 800 AD. Charles Dickens contributed to the revival of this holiday in Britain with his novella about Ebenezer Scrooge. For 10 points, name this Christian holiday celebrating the birth of Christ.", "answer": "<b> Christmas</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>This man adopted Olive Risley after rumors of an affair between them grew. He served as Governor of New York during the trial of Alexander McLeod for his involvement with</b> <b>the (+)</b> <em><b>Caroline</b></em><b> affair. Lewis Powell injured this man during the 1865 assassination plot</b> <b>against Lincoln. He negotiated with (*)</b> Eduard Stoeckl to purchase an expanse of land deemed his\u201cFolly\u201d by detractors. For 10 points, name this Secretary of State under Abraham Lincoln who negotiated the Alaskan Purchase with Russia.", "answer": "William H.<b> Seward</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>One leader of this country compared it to a \u201cpatient in a cast\u201d and to himself as a\u201cdoctor.\u201d This country\u2019s government lost support after it failed to deter an invasion of an island nation led by (+) Archbishop Makarios III. It\u2019s not Poland, but after exiling King Constantine II to Rome, this country\u2019s government from 1967-74 was called the\u201cRegime of the (*) </b> Colonels.\u201d This country\u2019s EU-imposed austerity is opposed by its Syriza party. For ten points, name this country whose military junta under Georgios Papadopoulos ruled from Athens.", "answer": "Kingdom of<b> Greece</b> (accept<b> Hellenic Republic</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}